<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sides | Unintended Consequences]]></title>
  <link href="http://p5k6.github.io/blog/categories/sides/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://p5k6.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-15T10:26:16-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://p5k6.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Stanfield]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pork Tenderloin Experience]]></title>
    <link href="http://p5k6.github.io/blog/2015/06/18/pork-tenderloin-experience/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-18T12:14:47-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://p5k6.github.io/blog/2015/06/18/pork-tenderloin-experience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>I&rsquo;ve been watching Good Eats a bit of late</h3>

<p>There&rsquo;s a handful of episodes on Netflix now. So - I tried <a href="http://www.foodnetwork.com/recipes/alton-brown/grilled-pork-tenderloin-recipe.html">one of Alton Brown&rsquo;s pork tenderloin recipes yesterday</a>.
But - I wasn&rsquo;t quite sure what to serve as a side.
In the past, I&rsquo;ve been partial to pineapple (love some grilled pineapple!).
However, I also had some leftover rice in the rice cooker, still hot from the previous day.</p>

<p>So - I tried something a little different. I added the rice to a mixing bowl, then added the reserved marinade from <em>after</em> post-grill marinating of the pork, to the rice.
I then took about &frac12; of the grilled pineapple and cut them into chunks, adding them to the rice mixture.</p>

<p>I personally really enjoyed the meal. The pineapple adds a sweetness that offsets the strong sour flavor from the lime.
There was also enough salt in the leftover marinade for me; this is something that would be easy to overlook though.
I wouldn&rsquo;t be afraid to add additional salt if I felt it necessary.
The rice was a bit strong by itself (it&rsquo;s quite sour - the pineapple <em>really</em> is necessary, err on adding more pineapple than you think you need).</p>

<p>For dinner, I served the rice/pineapple/marinade mix separately; however, for leftovers, I chopped up some leftover pork and added it to the rice mix (as it is a nice addition to the rice mix).</p>

<h3>Pineapple/Pork marinade rice side recipe (makes about 4 servings)</h3>

<h6>Ingredients</h6>

<ul>
<li>leftover marinade from pork tenderloin (the half used to marinate <em>after</em> grilling the tenderloin)</li>
<li>about 3 cups cooked rice (probably could have used a little more, as the marinade is quite strong)</li>
<li>about &frac12; of a grilled pineapple, cut into bite size chunks</li>
</ul>


<h6>Directions</h6>

<ul>
<li>Mix all of the above together in a mixing bowl right before serving</li>
</ul>


<h3>Notes</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Do not use the marinade used with the raw pork</strong></li>
<li>I served with a slice of pork tenderloin, and the rest of the pineapple as a second side</li>
<li>I might experiment with using <em>all</em> of the pineapple in the rice bowl in the future</li>
<li>Trying 4-6 cups cooked rice, whole pineapple and the marinade might be a good idea</li>
<li>Reheats decently in the microwave; not the best I&rsquo;ve ever had, but certainly not the worst (in terms of &ldquo;how good reheated is&rdquo; vs &ldquo;how good original was&rdquo;)</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
